[Music]
so I want to do a very short standalone
clip in response to something that
Daniel SH macton Berger was sharing in
the war on sense-making pieces which
were all about how the information
ecology is damaged and what we need to
start doing about that how we might
start getting a more healthy information
ecology I've been thinking about some of
the like rural omega being one of those
things like giving giving someone the
benefit of the doubt and hoping that by
doing that can start to tease out the
meaning and then we go enter sort of
into subjective sense making process
together that's more than the sum of its
parts I was thinking about whether
there's a rule Omega for interpersonal
dialogue and I was also thinking about
how like in my personal life I've kind
of evolved towards a rule of not to say
and if this is about gossip as well and
there's a really interesting question
about kind of what the value of like you
could call it gossip or talking about
other people plays there's a there's a
lot of thought about that that it's
actually quite it's a really valuable
thing for communities to do because it
helps police or enforce boundaries in
terms of our interactions with each
other knowing how people have treated
others in the past and that's a really
interesting kind of area
I think the sapiens guy writes about
gossip in that way at how it's a really
really important thing you Val know
Harare and so my kind of nascent rule
Omega is I try if I have something that
I will say about someone I will make
sure that I've said that to that person
like I don't feel comfortable saying
something about someone that I haven't
actually said to their face and that's
something that I've kind of evolved
towards of like what feels right for me
in terms of when I realize I'm talking
about someone behind their back or
whatever it's like I feel comfortable
saying something as long as they're
aware of that I've had that conversation
with them and then given them a chance
to respond made it clear what my
position is if you imagine that as a
gonna rule Omega rule a rule Delta or
something like that for interpersonal
relations it does feel like that starts
to tidy up the information ecology the
because you know when you're expressing
something if you're all behaved kind of
agreeing to that rule you know that
anything that you've heard has been
expressed to that person it like clears
out it starts to clear out a lot of the
he-said she-said we said but you're not
supposed to know this order than
whatever and also I think that's part of
that's part of being more centered being
more honest being like more grounded in
in our lives when we're not having to
keep track of who knows something and
who knows something else and then which
story we've told to this person if we're
allowed to share it with that person
it's like that is a huge weight of
storylines for us to keep in our minds
at all times and it's really exhausting
and really sort stops us being really
present in our lives a lot easier
as Jordan Peterson talks about if you or
him towards truth it makes things a lot
easier in our lives because there's a
lot of stuff you don't have to keep
remembering all the time but then as
Daniel explained in the second Warren
sense-making almost anything can be
weaponized I want to go into some of the
exceptions on that as well but when I
was when I was following this sort of
this thought pattern of okay that could
be a rule Omega for interpersonal
dialogue if you know that you're talking
about someone it's like and it's also
something we can then kind of enforce
with each other if you hear someone
saying to you oh well this person did
that or though though they're like this
you can say well I actually have used
have you shared that with them like I
find myself doing that more and more
it's like well if you're telling me this
have you had that conversation with that
person and then asking that person to
maybe if you're going to share that with
me you should really let them know you
should have that conversation and I want
to go into kind of the exceptions
because there's always exceptions to
this rule but I was really struck when I
kind of followed this this this kind of
train of thought that that's also a rule
that's kind of evolved as one of the
cardinal rules of journalism it's called
right of reply that you learn very early
it's like if you have any comment or or
claim about anyone in an article one of
the rules you have to put it to the
personal a corporation or the the
individual or whatever before you
publish it so you have to get the right
of reply and you have to put that into
your article which feels really fair
like it and it's interesting that that's
evolved as kind of naturally over time
as a as a rule of within journalism
which is which is part of the
information a call
there's another thing that came out of
the war of sense-making too so that
Daniel smacking burger said which then
it kind of hit home for me after I heard
a phrase just randomly which was
emotions or not instructions I thought
huh it's really interesting because I'm
a mindfulness instructor as well but I
also do you know the kind of work we do
as counselors and the inner growth work
is very much around what am I feeling
right now and bring that out but as
Daniel pointed out everything can be
weaponized so emotions can be weaponized
and emotions emotions are very complex I
think in terms of like a principle or
rule for inter relating emotions and on
instructions is really nice phrase
because the person I heard it from
described it as they're really important
you can listen to your emotions you need
to be absolutely connected with what
they are you know have some objectivity
of you know being able to say okay I'm
feeling angry I'm feeling whatever it
might be but they're not instructions in
the sense of you don't have to then
react to them and that's really a core
tenant in in mindful self-awareness is
that it comes up you observe it and then
you decide what to do that is absolutely
crucial that that's called decentering
as part of D centering where I can take
that step back that's crucial for
interpersonal dialogue because otherwise
emotion could be weaponized in pretty
much every sentence it's like well I'm
feeling like this and you're not
acknowledging it and therefore I have a
right to get angry at you or I've right
to do this I've right to do that so yeah
so that's a tenant I've really been
thinking of and realizing that that it's
been quite core to to my own practice
and you know it's big and stoicism as
well it's it's a very important skill
that we develop you but I want to talk a
little bit about some of the exceptions
even that rule can be weaponized like
I'm I'm aware in myself there's been a
couple of times where I've shared
something with someone or I've had a
confrontation with someone and there's a
part of me that's like are great now I
can and how I can talk about that person
to anyone and I can say this to anyone
like there is a kind of like being
really aware of how we're using that
rule still has to come in so I can think
of a couple of times where there's been
a sort of mischievous part of myself or
kind of vindictive part of myself that's
like right now I've told that person now
I can say whatever I want about them so
that's you you can't bypass any of those
kind of weaponization with that
and there's also the danger of are you
sharing there's also kind of meta ruled
all of this rests within is there has to
be an understanding of when you're
sharing that information with someone
are they going to use that information
for the benefit of everyone involved so
we're part of various communities that
have done we did counseling training
with groups of people we've we've got
these kind of relationships with people
where we're having these kind of
conversations and we're asking for
reflections from others about our kind
of negative patterns and what we kind of
what they're observing and they're
really useful and very oriented towards
growth they're really helpful to have
those relationships but if you're
sharing stuff about other people and
they haven't bought into like they're
still gone and maybe there's part of
them it's motivated by resentment or
vindictiveness or some kind of wanting
to get one up on that other person there
are certain people that's not safe to
have that kind of relationship with and
have it knowing where that is and can
and the most sort of obvious examples
are like the sort of what you might call
the personality disorder spectrum where
someone's got such a fragile sense of
self that they will kind of weaponize
and manipulate and and like that's the
extreme but there's also there's
probably a cut-off point where what what
differentiates healthy healthy feedback
healthy gossip from unhealthy gossip
there's a dividing line and it's
somewhere in the place of is that person
trust able not to act out in that way
yeah it is interesting as you're talking
what I'm thinking of is the fact that
this idea that anything can be
weaponized and also how often I see in
myself and in various communities how
models are used to principles models
rules of engagement even something like
rule Omega whatever it might be
are used to bypass being human you know
so these things all get tested on the
battlefield so to speak they get tested
in life and for me the only thing that's
worth is salt is is our actions you know
so it comes down to very human values of
you know what's how much integrity have
I got how you know how honest am I how
you know how open am I you know how can
I admit making a mistake
etc and
so I always find it very interesting to
see people under pressure or in
challenge and that's how I test my own
values it's like okay well how are you
when money's on the line you know that
brings up a whole lot of shadows for
people that's like oh
and suddenly everything can fall out the
window all these lofty goals and so
that's the bit where I think the real
practice happens and I think that's you
know we've talked about this concept of
coherence of falling out of coherence
I actually thinks when we fall out of
coherence that we learn the most in a
lot of ways and so being able to come
back into some kind of sovereignty and
centrist and go oh I really lost my
there I wonder what that was about like
that's the important thing it's not
never losing our because that's
gonna happen and that's part of growth
yeah and that reminds me of something
daniel said I think in the first war on
sense-making
about he trusts people to the level of
their worst behavior like knowing that
assuming that everything goes
pear-shaped what's the what how bad will
you allow it to get how vindictive will
you allow yourself to be how and that's
a really interesting that's a really
good frame I think to kind of look at
this through so this has been a lot of
fun we should do more of these yeah I'm
really interested to hear people's
thoughts reflections on this
particularly Daniel do you think that
this is potentially workable as a rule
Delta and if not which seventeen things
have we not taken into account cool it's
big seen well done for making it to the
end I just wanted to let you know a few
things we've got coming up including the
biggest event we've ever done the rebel
wisdom festival which will be a mix of
ideas and dialogues between people like
Daniel Shmack Tim burger Bonita Roy
Rupert Sheldrake Jamba Vicky and many
more and because wisdom isn't just
intellectual it's also about practice
will be offering experiences like
circling different interpersonal
dialogue mindfulness breath work and
many other with world-class facilitators
we're also running our first online
course called sense making 101 and if
you're enjoying the content you can help
us make more by joining the rebel wisdom
club which will give you discounts on
the courses and the events and also
access to a load more content on the
website including all of our live events
it'll also give you access to our
growing community
which is something we want to make a
real focus for 2020 adding more meetups
and other services for members so I hope
you enjoyed the film and see you soon
you